welcome to voices with reveille key
today I'm very excited because we're
going to get into a topic that I've
alluded to many times in both my video
series awakening from the meeting crisis
and to other discussions I've had and
that's going to be around the coda
school in particular nishitani and his
book religion and nothingness and I'm
gonna this to do this I was proposed to
me by Jarrod Morningstar so welcome
Jared why do you tell us a little bit
about yourself
hi John thanks for having me really
excited to dig into some interesting
East Asian philosophy with you
right so I'm Jared I have a background
in in religious studies formerly and
since that education I've been trying to
continue my studies and keep building
community around some of these sorts of
topics so just just a few months back I
finished a an online book club on
occasion issue Tony's religion and
nothingness mm-hmm and it was it was
really an impactful read for for both
myself and and the other participants
there this wasn't my first time with
this text it was the first time that I I
read it in full cover to cover but I'd
read large portions of it previously in
some upper-level Buddhist studies
classes so I had some some preparation
coming in and I think that was that was
really good but it's it's certainly one
of those texts where without knowing a
decent bit about Buddhism in general and
in particular Mahayana tradition and
then also Western philosophy
Christian theology might be really kind
of having a hard time swimming through
it so I'm I'm looking forward to being
able to sort of taking some of these
major themes and ideas out in
conversation here so that they're
hopefully a bit more accessible
that's great that's well put yeah I
similarly have read with others religion
and nothingness twice it's it's as I
thought as I said before I put it in
terms you know the top five books I've
read in my life up there with you know
Plato's Republic and Platina says in
needs or something like that
that's how and somebody who is aware of
religion and nothingness as you are
would probably see just how prevalent it
is throughout the entire of awakening
from the meeting crisis mm-hmm
nish attorneys had just a profound and
deep influence and continues to on my
thinking as I was preparing for today I
was going over some stuff and I was
realizing a lot of these.i stuff that I
come up with these ideas when I go back
and I realize oh yes I ultimately got
these it was inspired by mr. tani so I
feel at some point although I do you
know give him credit and praise and I
need to I need to cite him more because
of the profound influence he had on me
so for those of you who don't know the
kyoto school is a japanese school of
philosophy well its philosophy in the
ancient sense of philosophy as much as
conceptual analysis it's about
philosophy as a way of life that is
conducive to wisdom enlightenment self
transcendence etc so it's it's one of
those things like Buddhism itself at
least certain guises of Buddhism that
straddles the boundaries between what we
normally separate as philosophy and
religion and the hero school attempted
itself to be a deep bridging between
Buddhist philosophy especially Zen
although Pure Land Buddhism has some
influences too but especially Zen and
[Music]
continental philosophy especially the
work of for nishitani of Heidegger James
is also deeply and William James is also
deeply influenced all
on the schita so James and Heidegger are
deeply influential later people like
muscle obby are also familiar with
whitehead and Tillich and so there's an
attempt to get beyond through synoptic
integration the limitations of both
Eastern and Western philosophy if you
allow me to use those adjectives so this
is of course a very pertinent for us
today
very very pertinent but what's
especially pertinent about nishitani is
that he focuses on the problem of
nihilism as the central problem that he
wants to address by bridging Eastern and
Western philosophy together so of course
Heidegger and Nietzsche loom large from
the Western tradition but various
aspects about emptiness and no no
thickness which will force Jared and I
will get into from the Zen tradition or
also figuring very largely in his work
just before we get into it I would not
have you have not read any of this for
the background picking up and reading
religion and nothingness is very very
hard as Jared indicated mr. Thani
presupposes a very literate a reader
somebody who's very familiar with out
with with a few things one is sort of
Heidegger Ian Nietzsche and Heidegger
Ian of continental philosophy to some
degree the Neoplatonic tradition this
this figures in Neesha Tony's work quite
a bit and you'll see it also in
commentators on nishitani making that
connection
Suzuki DT Suzuki was sort of a
figurehead of the Kyoto School often
made comparisons between zen and a car
meister eckhart a neo platonic christian
so you need to understand that and then
of course you need to have some deep and
it can't be just conceptual you need to
have a participatory experience you need
to have practiced and lived within some
of the ecologies and practices of
Buddhism and to some degree Taoism and
then only then
are you really really in the place where
you can read this terrifically profound
book but I would recommend a couple of
books for people as good introductions
Robert Carter is an excellent guide to
the kyoto school and this book the kyoto
school in introduction by Robert E
Carter who actually taught at Trent
University here in Canada yay Canada
this is an excellent book he's booked on
Nishida the nothingness beyond God is
also excellent and then as a second
introduction I recommend this book by
John Strom ba the formless the formless
self is also very good introduction and
then there's also a couple of
anthologies there is called the Buddha I
which is an anthology of essays I should
this is an anthology of essays by people
in the Kyoto School and so I would
recommend getting some background
familiarity and those streams that I
mentioned maybe reading the Carter book
the strong ball book then perhaps try
the essays from the Buddha I and then
then I think you'll be in a place where
you could tackle our religion and
nothingness I'm not trying to build a
mystique around it I it's exactly the
opposite I think I am yet deeply serious
when I think this is one of the most
important books I've read in my entire
life many people regard it rightly as a
world historically important
philosophical text and again not
philosophy in the just conceptual sense
but and the life transformative sense so
I want to prepare you as much as
possible for a deep engagement so you
can really drink the depths of this book
and is really profoundly relevant to
what I've been calling the meeting
crisis so that's a little bit of a setup
just so people didn't get a background
and if this is very foreign to them as
it is liable to be this should give them
here's your here's the educational
pathway to get into what we're talking
about
hopefully this our discussion will serve
as a good introduction as well so Jared
I've been talking about I want to turn
thing
over to you for a bit well how would you
like to start in on this and start to
tackle it unfold it yeah just quick I
also have a secondary source
recommendation here very recently
republished just at the end of 2019 it's
a anthology of scholars responding very
directly to his religion and Nothingness
came out I think towards the end of the
80s there so the the the English version
of the book was was translated 83 I
believe it's a really unique translation
in that eunbong act work directly with
nishitani to create the translation and
there's even passages in the English
version that they sort of wrote fresh
that don't really appear in the in the
Japanese original so we're really
getting something authentic and and
unique in that translation but but this
anthology I'd say it would be a an
excellent sort of post reader after
you've you've gone through the text and
experienced it being able to go through
these essays which really deal with sort
of each each of the the different major
themes that nishitani hits on and and
helped to clarify some things in there
so I just about finished this one
and it's definitely helped me dig even
deeper so we definitely definitely
recommend at excellent so and you say
you that's good thing to sort of read
after yeah flexible religion and nothing
mystery it was sort of a reflective
reappraisal of it mmm-hmm okay that's
excellent I have not seen that an
apology so I'm going to order it once we
are done wonderful yeah it just popped
out at the the end of 2019 and I just
happened to get it in my Amazon
recommendations or something so very
very synchronous there great great
anyway where to where to begin with nice
G Thani I think maybe just a broad
overview of stuff some of these themes
might be
helpful especially the the major
concepts that that your viewers will be
new to Juniata and his his unique
approach to new Hilla t perhaps first
yeah I think most I think that would be
I mean that's gonna be the place where
most people are gonna find a sort of
immediate access coming in and out of
you know I mean as I said in my series I
wanted to include him as one of the
prophets of the meaning crisis but I
decided I'm gonna hold off on that
because I want him to be a star figure
in another series I'm working on which
is a series on non-theism and the
reinvention of me in terms of this
struggle with the meaning crisis and so
but yeah I see him I think the problem
of nihilism the problem of the meaning
crisis and he definitely gets it very
profoundly is a good place to start so
why don't we start there
yeah so this idea of ahilla T factors in
really pretty immediately in in his work
here and is a pretty consistent thread
all the way throughout and so basically
this isn't just a an idea of like a
psychological state of nihilism but it's
it's really an ontological reality here
that he's trying to describe though it
also does include this this
psychological component that we're more
familiar with but I think basically a
good way to start to approach this is to
consider it in terms of concepts like
finitude or death things that really
sort of have this immediate sense of
sort of the ground dropping out beneath
the meanings that were we're used to
swimming in within life and so this is
sort of a something Nietzsche Chinese
laying the groundwork for for them to
get some somewhere else which is this
standpoint of shewn yet
but in terms of the the nobility it's
this like really profound ontological
reality that sort of is the the reversal
of our sense of meanings are in the
sense of realness of things and such
this and being of them that we
especially in our Western philosophical
mind sort of very being focused take as
this very fundamental way that reality
is it is constituted great let's try and
unpack that a little bit more than four
people so there's a sense in which I
mean being a sort of sort of deaf
infinitude these are perennial aspects
of human being and they can cause people
to fall into despair and nishitani of
course means that and he doesn't mean
despair just psychologically he means
that like kirkegaard means it he means
this what I tried to get at this I'm not
saying it's adequate but this was my
stab at this was to talk about sort of
the breakdown of our cultural cognitive
grammar not only the individual project
but the shared projects by which we try
to you know lay the grammar for how
we're going to make sense and make
action and make persons right and all
that all of that fundamental cultural
cognitive grammar now it can come into
question individually for us when we
confront of the sort of crucial features
of absurdity renewal and nishitani of
course is talking about that but he's
also I mean it's also very clear he's
talking about a historical process that
has come to a particular point of
fruition especially within you know
Western society European society and the
figure of Nietzsche therefore looms very
largely so there's this idea that you
mishit on ease both pointing towards
individual despair but he's also
pointing towards the death of God right
and so he's talking about the two of
them together when he's talking about
the problem of nihilism at least to my
mind he's trying
you always remind he's always talking to
which is part of the beauty of his
writing is is he's often addressing you
as an individual but he's also
addressing the culture the world culture
as a whole at the same time mm-hmm yeah
it's it's a it's an incredibly like
multivalent idea this this ahilla t he's
he's bringing into play here and the way
he some sort of roots it's the
inevitability of it boiling up within
our current classical Western European
philosophical frameworks is is really
really phenomenal like going back to
Aristotle and the idea of substance as
sort of like the first like sort of step
in Western philosophy where being a very
being focused philosophical system was
really really cemented in and so this
isn't sort of a very like low resolution
kind of romanticism for tradition he's
really like plumbing plumbing the depths
back to to some of the very roots of
Western philosophical thinking and and
getting at things things from there so
yeah figures like like Aristotle Conte
is another big one who sort of tackles
and and sees as sort of furthering the
acceleration of some of the landscape
where nihility can can be especially
like easy to uprise there and i really
noticed that in your own series as well
with some of these same same figures but
yeah so Aristotle you get this very
substance oriented philosophical vision
which sort of ignores the the non-being
side for a more exclusive look of being
so realness it's constitu
I thinks being solely by substance and
then in incant you have then this sort
of divide much more between the the self
and the world and so then you have this
subject which is also a point which can
be considered as this like fundamentally
real thing within Western philosophical
tradition and nishitani z-- ideas of
morality function on both of those both
sides of that divide where the nobility
can can boil up it at the bottom of
things with substance and it can also
boil up at the bottom of the the subject
with with a self so that's good let's
try and talk about that that's really
good I like the way you just put that to
boiling up at the bottom so part of how
what I understood nishitani was saying
is we get a notion of of reality as
being and we understand being and this
comes to fruition and Cod as a kind of
autonomy a kind of solving owes it Ness
right and of course this comes to this
comes to us in the Cartesian ego in
which the right the the Cartesian self
is a completely self enclosed and we
have subjectivity that is completely
autonomous completely self enclosed and
then you get the sickness unto death of
creditor because mmm-hmm you have to
think of that subjectivity is an ever
tightening news right that you lose loot
right you're progressively moving
towards you know that that point and I'm
gonna make a bridge with this here you
know at which doubt is supposed to stop
when you get to sort of the the center
of the self the center of subjectivity
so the self enclosed in this way where
right it gets this point where it can go
no further and then that's what's most
real and that has permeated our culture
I mean that everything and this is one
of hydrators critique everything is is
subjectively centered right everything
is centered on human subjectivity and
serves it and so the problem I see
nishitani saying is when we have
that view of being where we were where
we transform hypostasis into substance
into right into is self-enclosed
right rather than that which stands
under but instead that which that which
stands under precisely because it is
enclosed upon itself right and you can
see how this comes to fruition right and
each is will to power that everything is
so enclosing upon itself and all it's
doing is just expanding itself right it
theirs right so there is no relatedness
to anything else so the idea is because
we're like that and we see this in
descartes when right when we encountered
the existential doubt when we encounter
an absurdity the grammar of our culture
drives us inward to this point right and
then it tells us to stop there and then
we are we are bereft we are absolutely
cut off by that existential doubt we are
absolutely isolated not only from the
world and other people but from our self
because anything outside right of our
pure present subjective experience is
subject to doubt subject to absurdity
right and then mr. Tony's point is that
when we might call it psychological
existential doubt hits the that the way
that grammar drives us we are then stuck
we are deeply stuck and that's what he
sees our problem of nihilism is that we
get to a place where the doubt is stuck
and when the nihilism is is stuck and we
we're jet we're we're just trapped and
out of loss and and so I think the
central thing to to to turn to now and
this was a title of a one of his earlier
books is the self overcoming of nihilism
that nishitani is great insight was you
can only owned it you can only overcome
nihilism by taking it through to its
depths but our fixation on the self
sustaining self enclosed missed the pure
actuality of be
right and which means it has no
receptivity no relationality at that
cultural cognitive grammar and it and
its inherent atomic subjectivity means
that we can't actually take nihilism
deep enough so that we can overcome it
and this I think is one of his
profoundest insights all of our attempts
to try and assert this fundamental
grammar in the face of nihilism they all
collapse because everything we try to do
just circles goes through the same
process and we circle back in and then
we're trapped here again and we're
completely cut off we're completely
isolated and nothing matters to us and
nothing means anything to us and so I
was trying to get at that with in the
series you can see the influence I was
trying to get you know how we get
trapped in this process that slowly
strangles us and we keep running the
grammar faster and faster only to find
it we could the noose gets tighter and
tighter around us mm-hmm yeah I think
his his critique of Descartes here is is
particularly yes relevant and how he
sees what de cartes project ultimately
did is his place like confine us to this
field of the cogito or the field of
cognition and so everything that we are
apprehending is is very much in this
self enclosed and related back to the
self and so ultimately when we encounter
this ahilla T we parse it through
through our our self and when you have
this dynamic of nahele t and the self it
it it really just keeps you stuck there
in in that nihilism because naturally I
mean in our self-centered ways we really
resist this this ahilla T that's coming
up because we see it
really eroding the the meanings and even
the very beings of the things that are
that are most important in our lives but
ultimately what what nishitani wants to
do is achieve this radicalization of of
Manila tea that he calls the the
convergent Shunyata or emptiness I want
the great note there's yeah through the
great doubt there and so no longer is is
the ontological reality of Manila tea
which is like a very like part of the
fabric of reality as much as beingness
is and so he sort of traverses through
that not on the the field of cognition
but on through this much more
existential mode where it's not always
relating back to the self and things are
able to be encountered on their their
own home ground and so when when this
process is is achieved here this aspect
of melody is sort of blown up it's
opened up yeah it empties itself through
its own bottom there and so on this new
field of emptiness it's that you have
like paradoxical the two sides of things
like co-arising and Co supporting
together and so it's really this aspect
of melody that like ultimately like
constitutes of things real being and
it's realness and it's like so let's
look at that excellent excellent
it's this is really fun let's again try
and unpack that step by step yeah okay
part of what I see is that the way and
and member we inhabit this worldview in
it it's it's it's it goes into the very
way in which we inhabit our own bodies
in mind right it's deep habit us right
and so everything's coming into question
but we've been tutored by Descartes and
coming out of the long history and
reinforced by Conte that
one thing that doesn't come into
question is the self right so the self
is regarded as substantial the subject
of all the predicates right this and so
what doesn't come into question is the
self and then nishitani x' point is
insofar as you do not let the
questioning the niala t come into the
self the self is always deeply other to
reality it's there's complete lack of
conformity complete lack of contact so
this this attempt to preserve the
substantial self at all costs licensed
by Descartes and Conte then of course
means that the process right the process
of meaninglessness or the expansion of
absurdity is not allowed into the self
itself and and and furnish itani that's
that's the great that's the great
mistake and that's the great and instead
what we do and this is I think where his
critique of Nietzsche comes in is
everything goes down to here and then
our response is our then the self should
push out even harder right it should
will to power and well I make the
meaning and I am Who I am
and right and and and right and so
that's that's our response a weak and we
and our culture sort of really valorizes
that right and then issue tony says no
that's that's a mistake the mistake is
right is and you're exactly right Jared
it's this is not just and this is not a
merely intellectual or even cognitive
process this isn't an existential this
is a modal process you have to let that
and this is where the connection to
Socrates is so profound rambha and her
book actually directly makes this
connection she says that meaninglessness
can be our basically our Socrates if we
if we if we are willing to let it if we
are willing to really confront it and
let us write and if
many of the dialogues would happen as
people make baked they close off in the
confrontation with Socrates right but
those who really absorb the aporia right
they actually write they they allow the
self to come into question and then what
nishitani says is you discover right you
discover something of the self and we
can talk more about that in a minute
but here's here's that here's even
before you get to that he says there's a
moment and you can see glimmers of this
in camu right where there is there's the
beginning of a recovery of the contact
with reality because the absurdity is
now right indwelling the self as opposed
to just being resisted by this self
right and so there's a deep there's now
an opening up there's a breaking of the
imprisonment in ego centrism because
there's a level at wit and this is gonna
be one of his big themes where you know
something by becoming it you know you
don't know it by representing it or
willing it or expressing it you know it
by becoming it and so you go from
knowing the absurdity as an object
remember what object means right
throwing against resist right you and
you don't just know it subjectively as
your feelings about the object you
actually become it I would say
transductive lee and so you become the
absurdity and then the idea is that
breaks you out of that ego centrism and
it gives you the first sense of that
right the absurdity can only have done
that precisely because there's a way in
which you and reality right are you know
it by becoming it so this is where I got
this from nishitani plays on the word
realization all the time good yeah he
plays on the word realization all the
time right it's so that realization that
I just talked about that realization of
absurdity is both the act of me
understanding and the act of it becoming
actualized in me right not a
representation but you know part of my
being I know it in my being what I call
the participatory knowing I know like I
say you can see that even in Camus at
the end of the stranger
um what he's talking about all about
absurdity and everything but he has he
has like that mystical experience where
he wants everybody to hate him because
he right and you can see that the the
there he gets a sense of the absurdity
within and the absurdity without her
starting to resonate so even in camu you
I think you at that you start to get a
sense of that that's controversial but I
I think that's that's that's one of my
takes so I take that to be there's two
things that are happening in that moment
we are we are discovering first of all
the the loop because with the great
doubt reveals that the autonomy and self
enclosing nests of of our subjectivity
of our self-consciousness of all that
stuff right is not metaphysically
necessary right it is it there there
because it presents itself as the only
game in town right right and there is no
it's not and it and that is that is that
is coupled to is bound up with this
rediscovery of the depths of
participatory knowing that we know
things by becoming them rather than them
resisting us are we willing them or us
just representing them with
intersubjectivity there's this deeper
kind and this is the influence of both
of Heidegger and Buddhism on him there's
this deeper kind of knowing the deep
kind of participatory knowing suddenly
is realized by us and so the great doubt
I think it's like this like this pivotal
move yeah so I I just I was trying to
unpack what you were what you said about
it oh it's much deeper and it's more
than just a psychological thing and how
it's right because I'm trying to and I'm
not telling you what to say you say what
you want to say but I'm trying to
translate a lot of nishitani x' terms
like home ground and think about it into
something that might be more directly
accessible to the people who are
watching yeah he certainly has
a handful of coinages and then also
these like classical Buddhist terms that
do do need some some increased
accessibility for a lot of people I'd
say yeah in terms of this sort of
dynamic of Shunyata we're getting into
it's it's so it's so fascinating and
it's and it's so hard to grasp by the
very nature of it becomes be he I mean
is very explicit that this can't be a
representational reality right when we
we make Shunyata into a thing like
emptiness by its its nature is no thing
yeah and so we're already off on the
wrong foot there so trying to like
grapple with this concept and even apply
it is very very tedious and difficult
and and really has almost a poetic
element in it I feel I think it's that I
think I mean this is why I brought up
this notion of realization and yeah in
the trans jected sense because Shunyata
is is never a representation it's never
a thing it's always it's always I don't
want to say it's something see the
language is ah right but it's always
within realization right it's right
there it's not it's not it's not
something realized right um it's not
it's yeah it's the it is the the very
seen use of the real of transgender is a
tion
see the thing that he wants us to
realize is that well maybe I mean in any
not so much him but Ave makes it a lot
of connections to Tillich right and the
idea that the self is ultimately
mysterious and reality is ultimately
mysterious in a deep way and it's only
by accepting that the loss of the self
enclosing this of the self within that
we can then let we could we can actually
realize the mystery the depths of
and so it's important that Shunyata I
mean this is difficult
well the adjective I want to use but i
wanted i want to give his definition
first he defines religion as really self
realizing reality right and he's right
so you know it's where which wears what
is absolutely foregrounded is the trans
ejected realization that we were just
talking about a few minutes ago and how
it's opening things up in their depths
and it's opening them up beyond any way
in which there's they we have a fixed
closed representation or grass funding
right and so that's what he means by
religion so the the event of Shunyata is
religious it's religious right you it's
so for him there is no way of coming
into relationship with Shunyata that
does not carry with it deep mutual
transformation of oneself in the world
yeah yeah i to try and put it succinctly
with some of these these main terms he's
using we start at being and we encounter
in ahilla d which is ultimately just
this like aspect of reality as much as
being is but because we're caught up in
this self enclosed cognitive grammar we
resist this this aspect rather than
integrating it into ourselves and our
world experience and when we can
integrate that we have both the melody
and the being in in mutually self
arising for each other so ultimately
being is constituting the nihility and
the new hill ADIZ constituting being and
this is really what this field of
Shunyata is it's this what it's the
field beneath both those fields that
makes them able to be real for
themselves through the other and that
that analysis then it extends on the
field of Shunyata for for any any
particular
the fire that that burns burns because
it does not burn itself yeah and and and
and any self that you have grasped is
not is not the self right and anything
so this is what yeah so let's let's dig
into that a little bit because there's a
sense in which right
everything has a double aspect right
everything everything is well it's he's
picking up on the Zen idea
well actually goes back to Nagarjuna
right the form is emptiness emptiness is
form and and that the two are
inseparable inseparable from each other
and this is often talked about as a kind
of non duality so let's do the you know
the fire it's only the combustion only
exists because of the elements within it
that don't combust or the eye only sees
precisely because it's not looking at
itself if it was looking at itself it
couldn't see so and this is this is this
is also from The Tao HN right it's the
emptiness in the cup that we actually
are making himself but of course the
emptiness wouldn't work if the cup
wasn't possible so let's do but this
thing about the eye because he uses that
one quite a bit those from the western
to religious traditions might like the
the fire better because it's like the
burning bush in the Bible a fire that
burns though it has never burned up
right but the thing about the eye is its
it's usually a little bit more apparent
to people and I can punt on it a little
bit
yeah it's precisely that right it's the
ADI the one thing the eye cannot see is
itself and only and not seeing itself is
it capable of seeing other things so the
the the substance of the eye itself its
ability to see is actually born from the
fact that it's not self enclosed that it
is not autonomous that it is not bound
or in fully it is not fully subject to
itself all right that if it was fully
subject to itself caught in its
subjectivity
it would have
course never ever see so they're hot
there is always there is always though
that which is not the eye at least if we
understand the eye is that which sees
that actually makes it beady eye and so
everything has for nishitani this sort
of double aspect it has both you know
what it is that's its form but it's
inherently bound up
he caught right with what it's not and
that the way it's what it's not is how
it's open to everything else other than
itself and his point is those two are
absolutely inseparable and front as you
said from Aristotle long week we we took
the one and we try to exclude it from
the other we we made that its form and
the way it encloses itself is completely
separate from how it's open to other
things in this sheet on you say no no
everything is actually like that hmm and
for me that what I sort of God from
nishitani is that realization in this
itani sense of the realization of the
double effectiveness of everything is
precisely what allows that fundamental
ah that fundamental aspect shift where
we go from no thickness as privation to
no thickness as the shining of
everything the disclosure of everything
yeah and the other aspect that's not so
focused on the one particular thing but
more the like thing in the design is
that the being the home ground of the
particular object is is constituted by
the the existence and reality of all
other things and vice versa
the particular thing is is the he uses
this language of Master and servants so
all other things are the servants of one
particular thing and its home ground and
it is the master of all other things and
likewise vice versa yeah and so oh no no
but that's
I mean that that's that's that you know
that that's the classic that's indras
net right mm-hmm
that comes out and so yeah the idea
there is yeah the circum and sensuality
of everything so so the language I've
been trying to use to get this is you
the thing unit so there's a more nesting
and then more nests right is part of it
is it's common to totally explosive
relationships and with everything else
right but but there but that more nests
is also in the mission he does use this
word a lot when you talked about how how
you know that what something is is
arises in terms of how its open to
everything else but that doesn't become
an amorphous from our generous blob
right it's not just sort of right right
it's think so them the more nests also
comes into this such that's the way so
think about think about like and this
when things are beautiful alright so
when this is beautiful when this when
this strikes you is beautiful right
there's simultaneously that there's a
mortise to it I never knew cups could be
like this I never knew things were like
this right and your whole world is now
seen in a new light
but in this but but in the same token
and this goes this Collingwood emphasize
this this is the there's a sense about
which this is now non categorical for me
there's the suchness of this here
nowness that isn't captured by the
category of mug so they're
simultaneously there's so much more and
at the same time and it you know my
whole world is is lighted in a new way
but it's also there's the suchness of
this that this this is its I don't want
to use the word uniqueness because that
that goes back to the self enclosures in
this witness those two things and I mean
and that's a constant theme through
nishitani that sort of stereoscopic
vision like yeah right that way you're
always
look you know try to look through
subjectivity and objectivity to what's
beyond them look beyond the morning and
the suchness to what can only be
realized through them right look beyond
you know the the the the the the no
thingness and being to what can be seen
through them and of course it can't be
spoken in either one of those languages
or grammar it's only seen between them
so he I think this is the religious
aspect when we get that stereoscopic
seeing when we can see through both
aspects in this deeply ontological way
we come into the deepest conformity with
things we get into the deepest contact
with reality and that is the answer to
nihilism the answer to nihilism is that
deep that deep that profound realization
that deep contact with with Shunyata now
it's not even contact identification but
again not sort of disappearance like a
drop in an ocean right yeah one thing
that is is truly phenomenal about his
work here is just how he I mean he is a
very non dual like oneness kind of
oriented thinker but the like
fundamental respect for particulars that
is included within this this whole
thought system he presents his is is
just truly remarkable
yeah as you're reading him you just
really like as he's talking about a
particular like you you feel the the
oneness and that you really are he
really brings you into that that
profound contact there with the the
oneness through the particular and the
particular through the oneness yes well
so just this yeah and just this like
minoo it's it's it is a religious
experience to really like really read
that and the deep level and like get
that through through the text one way
that that I was able to come up with
using a metaphor to sort of explain this
matter
servant relationship he's talking about
is sort of through an analysis of
something like artistic photography or
painting so imagine scene one you have a
picture of a murderer with a knife
stabbing a victim the knife in this
picture is like such a subject element
and it is like supported by all these
surrounding elements in this in this
photograph where the all these different
figures the steam like dark alley at
night perhaps like constitutes the
specific being of this knife now picture
- you have a chef working in a kitchen
and a knife like against the wall with
other utensils and the knife in this
situation is is the the servant to other
aspects that are the master yeah yeah so
I think being able to just to see
because I think we pretty intuitively
experienced that in in art work there
how the background constitutes the
foreground and vice versa
and they can and they can and they can
invert and right right yeah yeah and so
his basic idea here is that everything
is always both the the knife and scene 1
and the knife in see yeah everything is
both he says that you know the middle
right everything is the center of
everything else which of course he also
talks about Nicolas of Cuza who you know
defined God as what the intelligible
sphere whose centre is everywhere and
whose circumference is nowhere mm-hmm
and because cruz' was also trying to in
learned ignorance he was trying to what
he'll do is he takes it takes opposites
and then he pushes them until the
opposition collapses and something
beyond it yeah is disclosed but when you
were talking about the oneness in the
more in the particular and the
particular and the oneness I mean for me
I mean two things were immediately
triggered one and muscle obby picks up
on this is white head you know white it
talks about the whole of the universe
collapses into one thing and then is
added like it's it's it's not a static
collapse everything comes
this and this adds something novel it's
such an it is the novelty of the
collapse of everything and then that
novelty gets taken up and everything
else is novelization if you'll allow me
a neologism and so made me think it made
me think of of that right away and then
like I said it made me think also of I
can't remember that the Chinese
patriarchs name the Andrews nap right
the idea that each jewel is the
reflection of all the other jewels right
and so yet nishitani it's interesting
now if you switch to the aesthetics of
his text his writing is actually to
trying to get you into that state of
mind that state of like when your state
of mind is kind of like Indra net-like
like indras net you've got this sort of
dynamic holographic state of mind and
it's only when you sort of realize that
state of mind does what he's like and
then you start to you start to I mean it
when when I say state of mind I
should've been doing this because it's
not a state of mind in your head it's
not an introspective state right it's
this Indra it's an existential state but
when only when you get that state of
being perhaps is better then you really
see what what he's talking about like
when you walk around the world and you
get that right and so I find reading his
text although very challenging again the
writers I really admire do that there's
the process of the text is as important
as the content and next yeah absolutely
and it's it's very winding process and
yes Bonnie here where you're not always
sure where he's taking you and then you
just kind of feel dropped off a cliff
sometimes and then like two chapters
later you realized you're back where you
were but in a different way now and yes
I mean it's it's certainly a challenge
but definitely a rewarding one the next
step he takes after sort of what we've
gone over at this point is is
integrating all this thinking like in
motion like in time in this text and
then he he close
up with with a really this is probably
the most challenging part of the text is
his analysis of history at the
historicity from like in Western
Christian and and post-enlightenment
perspectives and she's eternal
recurrence and like Buddhist more like
Universal Time and and karma like he
throws so much into this and his the way
he's able to end up with this idea of
history that's fully historical through
it's a historical eternal nature and
vice versa yet again is yeah that's I'm
still still grappling with that one for
sure yeah this stuff on historicity is
really really difficult I mean there's
the sense you get this sense that in the
movement I mean that was the name of the
book forms of transcendence the author
starts with an S camp number the name on
that author talks is doing sort of
comparing Heidegger to the mystical
tradition on the Neoplatonic Christian
mystical tradition and talks about how
like you can see history as this sort of
movement of paradigms right hmm these
shifts but that what can be disclosed in
that is as well if you'll allow me
something eternal hmm something that as
you move between the paradigms there's
something disclosed that is the giver of
paradigms which is not itself any
paradigm or in a paradigmatic and and
that that is really and that reminds me
a lot of Heidegger's notion of the being
that's not the being of beings but that
which gives the being at the ends so I
agree that's a difficult part of his
work I try to understand the the analogy
that works for me is is heidegger's
critique ovando theology then you
shouldn't understand two beings is not
some sort of Supreme Being it's not just
a super powerful being it is something
other than being but in no law in no way
separable from be a right if there's
Tina and so I think what he's trying to
do there he is
also see that which gives history is
therefore not historical which gives
history paradigmatically and not
historical is like is like that it's
it's it's not a secret history it's not
a soup it's not a secret author of
history it's it well it's the non
history that makes history possible
right and it's not separable from
history I thought that's what he was
trying to do and I thought that was
important because we in the West have
you know we have a very his store I
think there's a deep connection this is
you can see the influence of Heidegger
and Nietzsche and what I'm going to say
there's a deep connection between our
Anto theology our understanding of God
and our understanding of God as the
author of history and that reality
unfolds as a story as a history and
Misha Tony is very powerfully I think
and it's very difficult text I grant you
that but I think he's trying to
undermine those two things at the same
time together yeah yeah absolutely I
mean looking at the Christian view the
post enlightenment progress view and any
sheet on our Nietzsche's prints they're
all will based yes the areas of history
and will is this self enclosed self
centered concept and so he's trying to
to get beyond that and he even analyzed
as a karma in in the same way you know
at least parallel to this yeah in a
really important aspect but yeah it's
also important to consider that this non
historical basis for history isn't any
kind of Tilos of history exactly I was
about to say I was about to say that
because will and purpose and T loss are
bound together and the idea that yeah
yeah that's exactly right and even even
individual is understanding the the
meaning as ultimately having as a
purpose where the purpose is also
understood is that towards which they
will or that which the great will is
willing for them right yeah exactly
it's it's it's it's completely under
mining of a teleological notion of
history and God
and notice how difficult that is for us
to think in the West yeah how difficult
that is for us to thinking what the heck
would a non teleological history and a
non teleological god of history what
would that possibly mean mm-hmm yeah I
think somewhat like staying within that
paradigm but still like respecting his
thinking I feel like it almost has to to
do with every historical event and
occurrence being autotelic in itself
through all other things yeah it's it's
it's it's it's it's like that
it's like you move to the holographic
and this is what I get out of reading
like Latinas and Pro clothes right you
get and whitehead you get that sort of
holographic sense of history and then
what what you move to is you move off if
you allow me a metaphor you move off a
horizontal understanding of history to a
vertical understanding but it's more
spherical you look like if yeah yeah
right right
it's that sense of no no what history is
is one with the you know the disclosure
of the interconnectedness the
interpenetration of all things mm-hmm
yeah ultimately it has to be something
that that discloses both the genuine
historicity and uniqueness and newness
of events while also using this
universality yes yeah and and those
again are these self like reinforcing to
each other and they they constitute
there's being the universality and the
genuinely historical in particular so
yeah it's it's an incredibly deep view
of history and I see how being able to
integrate those two aspects would be
such such a powerful shift in in so many
domains of our thinking especially in
traditional religious and scientific
modes of thinking to be able to achieve
that that that non duality of these
these two
central features of history I think it's
central to his argument I mean I it's
not you know I think there's a reason
why that has to come at the end of
religion and nothingness because I think
he takes very seriously
heidegger's idea that the that
metaphysics is the history right
metaphysics is the history of nihilism
right and only by over by overcoming
that you know that Aristotelian
Cartesian Conti notion of metaphysics
and and overcoming the way it's bound to
our self understanding self
interpretation
can we actually overcome the nihilism
that has resulted from it so I think
although I agree with you that last part
of the book is the most challenging but
it is an important sense very summative
because that's where he's most putting
pressure on our cultural cognitive
grammar but where he feels like he's
deeply influenced by heidegger's thesis
right that this teleological substance
based way of thinking has really locked
us into the inevitability of nihilism so
he has to go there the demand he's gonna
really address nihilism especially the
meaning crisis of nihilism right the you
know the historical advent of it I can
to dominance right then he's got to do
that but that does mean that that the
only way I think I think he's correct on
this he sees he can do that is by deeply
challenging the cultural cognitive
grammar we have around history substance
being and God yeah with that I think
we've pretty much gone through this this
whole text in in its most important
themes here the only things we didn't
touch on we're ideas of the personal and
impersonal and the scientific
mechanistic analysis that he gets into
which is very very high daguerreian as
well yep very hard again but I think I
think we at least I mean and we were
both very we're both
very differential about you know you you
you can't just pick up religion well
maybe you can I couldn't I could not
just pick up religion and nothingness
and I had a quite sophisticated
philosophical education and you know
deep practice within Buddhism and Taoism
and it was no I took it takes a lot of
work and a lot of help from a lot of
other people so you know I'm offering
what we've we've done here together as
basically which we're trying to whet
your appetite and introduce you to I
think your relevance to the the problem
of nihilism and the meaning crisis is is
world historically important and is
profound had as I've said and we've seen
it repeatedly and this gave me a chance
to say it's had just a huge impact on me
and and my thinking and you know and he
for me is the great prophet in the way I
use it in the meaning crisis and the
biblical sense of prop he's the great
prophet on he's the great prophet of
non-theism he's really trying to say you
gotta break out of write that all those
things we've spent this whole time tried
to break out like you and I of you know
these sort of fundamental categories
right and break into something like and
on theism in a profound way and so
that's what I mean when I do their
series on non-theism and reinventing the
sacred in the face of my ilysm he's
gonna play a pivotal he's gonna play a
starring role in that series because
this is just such important work and
like and he uh he just read me also
represents the need we've got to get
past the Western and Eastern you know
approaches yeah we gotta break past that
and he for me is just a profound
exemplar of how that's possible for us
of how in the face of pluralism one can
get past kind of an easy perennialism or
an easy relativism and nishitani he says
look what can actually be done look what
can actually be done
yeah absolute it's sophisticated
the way he weaves Buddhism and
Christianity and with each Fleur and
he's very clear that he's not just like
a Buddhist based thinker just doing some
comparative analysis or something he's
he's finding the truth where it is and
bringing it together yeah he's not an
apologist for any he's not a Buddhist
apologist he's not a high to garyun
apologist he's not a Neoplatonic
apologist now he's doing like he hears a
epochal thinker and again this is not
sort of empty academic conceptualization
this is life transformative stuff he's
talking about mmhmm yeah very very
immediately even in in just reading the
text yep very much being able to those
those with ears to listen they are it
yeah that's for sure
okay Chad I think this is a good place
to bring it to a close perhaps we can
talk again about this or some of the
other figures in the Keota school but I
think this was a good introduction I
will probably want you to come back and
have another discussion with me when I'm
doing that series on on the god beyond
all gods and non-theism in the face of
nihilism so yeah that would be wonderful
okay that'd be great yeah I would I
would love to sort of apply some of
nishitani to some of the the major
themes you've been working with
especially the the religion that's not a
thank you yeah he's a star figure in
that so initial tani and Tillich and
Corbin so at some point we might want to
talk about well the possible discourse
between carbon and nishitani or you know
Corbin and Jung on one side and perhaps
nishitani and Nishida on the other yeah
that could that could be great I'm
actually just starting this coming
weekend a reading group on core bonds
alone with the alone so I'll I'll be
primed per for some comparative work
pretty shortly here some
okay that's great okay thanks a lot yard
yeah thank you really great pleasure